<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<game>
    <conversation>
        <text>ROBYN WILLIAMS: And now there is a new book to help you explore your neighbourhood, with sections on what you might find, how to proceed, and ways to share with explorers far and wide. The neighbourhood book is designed by Dr Zoe Sadokierski of the University of Technology in Sydney.

Zoe, if you went to Annandale, would you be surprised to find turtles there?

ZOE SADOKIERSKI: I would not, I actually go turtle hunting with my son down to Whites Creek, which is the area in Annandale that the turtles hang out most of the time.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: How did you know that?

ZOE SADOKIERSKI: Well, my friend who is actually in the office next to me, Jesse Adams Stein, lives there and she’s got a kid about the same age and she said if you ever get bored on the weekend, come down and we’ll go turtle hunting.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: Which brings me to your book, Creatures in your Neighbourhood: The Urban Field Naturalist Project. Now, the book is for me to take into the neighbourhood, and it’s a working guide, in other words you can look up what you’re seeing, there is a section on insects, birds, some of the obvious stuff, but also a guide for how to do it. And one of the things I find exquisite is that your first hint is to go slowly. How come?

ZOE SADOKIERSKI: Yes, as a team it’s an interesting mix. We’ve got two scientists, a field philosopher and two designers who have cowritten the book. And we came up with a set of steps on how to be an urban field naturalist early on, and the first one is to slow down, and I think in cities and urban areas we tend to…when we are outside we’re pretty busy, we’re trying to get from point A to point B, and we stop to slow down, look around and notice the little things that are going on at our feet, above our heads, sometimes even within our houses.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: It’s interesting, because if you go from your university, UTS, here and cross the road, you have a green building, one of the best-known ones in Australia, where you’ve got all sorts of plants coming out of the windows and roofs and what else.

ZOE SADOKIERSKI: It’s true, and one of the things that some people who don’t live in that building don’t know is that what comes with that is a whole bunch of other critters, including rats and birds and insects, because any time you plant stuff or sometimes when you don’t mean to, when the weeds pop up, they actually attract a whole range of creatures who come to hang out in that area, and I think that one of the things we’re trying to do in this book is get us to think about how we could be better neighbours to the creatures in our neighbourhood.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: I like the word ‘neighbours’ because that’s exactly what I do, and you’ve got a section on feeding creatures. Now, I feed birds, and you reference Darryl Jones’s work, he’s at Griffith University and he’s written a book on this sort of thing and I’ve interviewed him for The Science Show and he’s quite clear it’s how you do it, maintaining cleanliness, making sure you don’t give them junk or making them too dependent. Mind you, the birds who come to my place, there’s nothing dependent about them, they stay for about five seconds; oh, you’re not ready yet, all right, we’re off. But the interesting thing is it shows you who is in the neighbourhood, and there’s so many surprises. Is it 20 or 30 different species? Unpredictable.

ZOE SADOKIERSKI: Absolutely, and I think feeding birds or feeding animals is something that we just need to be educated about, to understand what they are supposed to be eating, to think about what we could feed them and doing things in moderation, which is pretty good advice for humans as well.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: You also mentioned the feral stuff like the rats and of course I mention perhaps foxes in some countries, they’re more populous in the cities than they are in the country. What do you do about them? Just observe them or what?

ZOE SADOKIERSKI: I think observing is a great start, and not just looking and saying there’s a fox, but looking at it and thinking about what is it doing, what is it up to? And that’s when I think it gets interesting, making the observation into a kind of story. And I think the fascinating thing about creatures in urban environments is that they are all adapting. None of them are supposed to live in cities, so if you start watching what they are doing, it can be really interesting, watching the cockatoos learning how to open bin lids to get access to some of our refuse food, but also fascinating things like watching crows who learn that if they sit on top of traffic lights and drop a nut, the cars will drive over it and then once the cars stop again they can go down and pick up the nut. Now, that is incredibly clever behaviour.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: It certainly is. But also some of the assumptions people make about what is a rat, there are plenty of ways in which you can be looking at something that’s native. And my partner, when she was on Catalyst, gave a whole bunch of cameras to people who thought that they had maybe a special native animal, and it was triggered by their movement and then we looked at their pictures to see how many were rats and how many weren’t, and it’s quite interesting, the variety you had beyond even the rat species.

ZOE SADOKIERSKI: Yes, and I think that that’s another thing that’s great, when we start observing closely and noticing things, not just what they look like but how they move, how many of them are hanging out together, what they’re eating, what they’re up to. Some of those things can start to give us clues about what these creatures actually are.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: Now, you designed the book and you did it not simply to make it more attractive, which it is, it’s a beautiful book, but also to help us use it. What’s your advice on how we use this wonderful book?

ZOE SADOKIERSKI: Well, there’s a section that’s on the different creatures, as you’ve mentioned, there’s a range of different creatures, to help you spot them and start to notice what they might be up to. But there is also a section on sketching and journalling activities, which is just a way to get people to start thinking about how they could actively observe things outside. So, some of the sketching includes things like doing movement maps, so watching how birds move around different areas or watching how snails might be moving in your garden. There’s a guide to snail homing where you put a little dot of paint on the back of the snail shells and watch how they move around. So, observation isn’t just with our eyes, it’s also thinking about what can we hear and what can we smell and how do we start to notice what things are doing or how they are moving around us.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: I like one of your headlines, I like several of them but one that particularly attracted me, which tells you quite a lot about me, 'Scrumptious Scat’. What is that?

ZOE SADOKIERSKI: There is another section of the book too where…the Urban Field Naturalist Project has a community aspect to it, so we get people to send in short stories, 200 words, of encounters that they’ve had with creatures in their urban environment and also plants or maybe looking at a sunset, and people send things in. And someone sent in this great story about looking at wombat poo and the idea of wombat poo being cuboid, it’s kind of square-shaped, and the reason for that is wombats find their burrows by smelling the poo, and round things roll away and square-shaped things don’t, so they’ve developed cuboid-shaped poo so it doesn’t roll away and they can find their hole.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: There’s evolution for you! Well, you talked about this to-ing and fro-ing with your readers, is that still going on? Is this a national project that you’re running?

ZOE SADOKIERSKI: It is a national project and it’s actually an international project. So it started during the first lockdown in Australia, and we opened the project up and invited people to send stories in, and one of the fantastic things is that we got stories from all around the country but also international stories started coming in. And there’s a few great stories about foxes from the northern hemisphere mostly, but also a really beautiful story from a teenager in India who watched a pair of birds nest in underpants hanging on the line outside her window, and she took photos of them for a month or three months I think and she watched the chicks hatch, and she captured the life-cycle of this pair of birds nesting in some undies on a washing line.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: And will this interaction keep going?

ZOE SADOKIERSKI: Yes, absolutely. So we put the book together as a way to tell people about this and give them, I suppose, some prompts, some instructions for how they might become urban field naturalists themselves, but we definitely encourage people to send stories in to the urbanfieldnaturalistproject.org. And we also run community programs where we’ve done some workshops at Taronga in Sydney, and we’ve done some workshops with Lost in Books in Fairfield. And we just want everyone that we can get to participate to come on board.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: What about the wide brown land, the rest of Australia?

ZOE SADOKIERSKI: Absolutely, I think the important thing with the book is that we’ve managed to get creatures in there that you will see anywhere you are in Australia, so we’ve got a really diverse range of creatures to make sure no matter where you are there’s things that you will spot. But the exercises as well you can do anywhere you are.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: And when it comes to youngsters…of course this is for old and young, but when it comes to youngsters, can you get them to put their screens down and just open their eyes?

ZOE SADOKIERSKI: Absolutely. I mean, I was testing this on my son who is now six, and particularly when our world became much smaller and we were restricted to a five-kilometre radius around our house, the world suddenly actually became a lot larger as we slowed down and we did sketching together. And I think kids actually really like being given an activity, and so do parents.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: Congratulations, and thank you.

ZOE SADOKIERSKI: It’s a pleasure, thank you for having me.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: Dr Zoe Sadokierski at UTS, and the book is Creatures in your Neighbourhood, highly recommended, with interactions attached.</text>
        <interlocutors>Robyn Williams, Zoe Sadokierski</interlocutors>
        <source>https://www.abc.net.au/radionational/programs/scienceshow/a-guide-to-the-creatures-in-your-neighbourhood/101347724</source>
    </conversation>
    <conversation>
        <text>ROBYN WILLIAMS: The Science Show on RN. And so we turn to the brain. First a glimpse from next week on a story we covered recently, how Elon Musk is keen to give us chips in our brains. Philosopher Frederic Gilbert has concerns.

FREDERIC GILBERT: We are very interested in understanding being implanted with artificially intelligent neural devices. It is unclear how these smart technologies are impacting and affecting our sense of agency, sense of understanding, the concept of identity for instance, which all have ramification in terms of some legal territories. If a device is, for instance, smarter than you in deciding or going to a specific alternative, does it mean that you are less responsible, less accountable, is it the device, is it the manufacturer, is it the programmer, the coder? So all these questions are quite interesting and in a way very novel actually.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: Saying, look, it wasn’t my fault officer, it was the implant in my head, the technology made me do it.

FREDERIC GILBERT: Exactly. We conducted an interview with an implantee, so we do have actually data that cover these observations, so we have got a human implanted in labs, and they report having the device manifesting false positives, so suddenly the device will start moving on its own without any intention from the patient. So these create very strange situations when the implantee will question themselves, will doubt themselves, will say, oh, perhaps I meant that, but that’s within a lab. But if you can imagine if you were sitting at a table, there’s a fork, there’s a knife, and suddenly the artificial limb that you are commanding with your mind is jumping on the knife instead of the fork and that leads to an accident, or a reprehensive act, who actually is responsible?

ROBYN WILLIAMS: Frederic Gilbert, and the consequences of brain chips. That’s next week. But your brain really does have a sort of surreal functioning. All you think you see is conjured in the grey matter and not connected directly to real events, somehow. And so is pain. Just listen to these thoughts from Lila Landowski, brain researcher, and one of our former ABC Top Five Scientists.

LILA LANDOWSKI: What if I told you that pain was all in your head? Sounds crazy, but if you imagine this scenario: so you’ve had the best day, you’ve got a promotion, your friend has sent you some beautiful flowers, you’ve got a hamper with your favourite cheese in it and it had chocolate in it, and you caught all the green lights on the way home. Then you walk through the door, and you stub your toe. Now imagine this; you have had the worst day, you’ve lost your job, everyone forgot your birthday, and you hit all the red lights on the way home, you’ve spilt your box of belongings from the office all over the doorstep as you get home, and then you stub your toe as you enter the house.

So which one is going to feel worse? Now, in the first scenario, after you stub your toe you mightn’t even flinch, but in the second scenario, you might actually just break down in tears. So why is this? Pain is a warning signal that tells us to escape a situation because we’ve hurt ourselves or there is a high chance that we are about to hurt ourselves, but pain isn’t just about what we sense, like what we physically feel with our bodies, the International Association on the Study of Pain defines pain as ‘an unpleasant sensory and emotional experience associated with actual or potential tissue damage’.

So, pain essentially is a combination of what our bodies sense about the world that we are in and it’s also at the mercy of being shaped by our thoughts and our emotions. And what this means is that pain is something that happens in the brain, and the best example of this is what we call phantom limb pain. So people who have had a limb amputated can still feel a very real and excruciating pain in the missing limb, even though the limb isn’t even there. So if pain only came from injury to the body, you would assume that having no limb means that surely you can’t have pain in that area, but clearly they do. So what we see profoundly impacts our experience of pain as well.

There’s this famous case in the British Medical Journal that explores what happened after a construction worker jumped onto a plank and ended up with a seven-inch nail through his boot. He was inconsolable, just the most excruciating pain. But after the surgeons carefully cut away his boot, they realised that the nail went in-between two of his toes, there was not a single scratch. And as soon as he was told this, the pain disappeared. So the visual image of seeing the nail go through his boot, seeing his horrified co-workers’ faces, the brain just talking all that information and it made a best guess, it decided that he was in danger, it gave him a very real and legitimate feeling of pain as a way of getting him to escape that danger.

So, pain and physical injury to our body can exist separately, and it’s cases like this that really reinforce this concept that pain is in the brain. We call this the biopsychosocial or the socio-psycho-biomedical model of pain. And what this means is our experience of pain is shaped by our social and our cultural context, by our psychological state, so our emotions and thoughts, and of course our biology. But that means that the biological part of pain, so, for example, the actual injury itself, is just one small part of what is actually happening, and that’s why using biological solutions like a pill for pain relief, for example, or surgery, that doesn’t always work or is only part of the solution.

So we can think of pain as being a bit like a volume knob; lots of things can turn that pain volume up, or it can turn it down. We know that pain is influenced by lots of things, like our anticipation of pain, how much sleep we’ve had, our anxiety levels or our mood, our attention, and even our genes. So, for example, when you are super absorbed and really engaged in a task, let’s say you are gardening and you love gardening, you might cut yourself and not even realise that you’ve injured yourself until you are back inside cleaning yourself up, and that’s actually not magic, that’s just your brain turning down that pain dial because you were paying attention to something else that you really enjoyed, you were using the part of the brain we call our prefrontal cortex to focus on that gardening.

Meditation and mindfulness can affect a person’s perception of pain in the same way by helping us focus on things other than that pain. When you’ve had an injury and you’re stuck in bed recovering and you don’t have anything else to distract you, that pain will feel objectively worse because you are otherwise missing out on your life, and your attention is focused on that injury.

Our perception of pain is also altered when we are engaging in our bodies fight or flight system. How many times have you seen an athlete have a fall or an injury in the middle of their race and you see them carry on heroically, seemingly oblivious to the blood pouring down their leg? This is because short-term stress, in this case from running that race, releases the neuromodulator noradrenaline into our emotion processing part of the brain called the amygdala, which can then turn down our sensation of pain.

Sleep is really important when it comes to pain as well. Not sleeping enough also lowers our threshold for pain, so we are more likely to feel the ache later at night after a long day, and pain will feel worse throughout the day if you’ve been up all night and haven’t slept properly.

There is even evidence that our genes affect our perception of pain. In fact, it’s redheads who seem to have the advantage here. There is a body of evidence that suggests that on average redheads have a higher threshold for pain. In fact a recent study in redhaired mice found that they can make less of a hormone that influences pain perception called melanocyte stimulating hormone, and this results in those mice having a higher pain threshold. And even if you aren’t a redhead, there is some good news; holding the hand of a romantic partner or even just being in their presence makes us have a higher pain threshold too. Love and pain are inextricably linked, and the brain registers the emotional pain of heartbreak in the same kind of way that it registers pain from a physical injury.

Anticipation also influences our perception of pain as well. If you warn someone that they are just about to experience some mild pain, like a needle for example, it won’t change anything, but if you tell them 20 to 30 seconds before the pain occurs, they can mentally prepare themselves and it hurts less. Now, if you were to tell them and then make them wait a few minutes, on the other hand that’s going to lead to anxiety, making the pain a lot worse. But that’s good because just like a bad day or bad sleep can make our feeling of pain worse, it means that the reverse is true as well. We have much more control over our experience of pain then you may have realised, and it hurts me to say this but we’ve been thinking about pain in the wrong way for way too long.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: Dr Lila Landowski who leads a team of neuroscientists at the Department of Medicine, University of Tasmania. And she was also once one of our ABC Top Five Scientists.</text>
        <interlocutors>Robyn Williams, Lila Landowski, Frederic Gilbert</interlocutors>
        <source>https://www.abc.net.au/radionational/programs/scienceshow/new-ways-of-thinking-about-pain/13924344</source>
    </conversation>
    <conversation>
        <text>ROBYN WILLIAMS: And so to a conundrum; what is harder than herding cats? Could it be putting one on a lead and going for a walk? Well, Alexandra Paton might disagree. Her field is photographing feral cats, stray ones, and those who’ve been wild all their lives.

ALEXANDRA PATON: The main focus of my PhD is improving and optimising our camera trapping methodology for studying invasive species, particularly feral cats, so we are talking species that have a home range, are far-roaming, have a low capture rate. Obviously there’s a lot of problems that come into play when trying to find these species using camera traps, the biggest one being that they might never walk by your camera. So I’m investigating things such as the use of lures, can we bring them in with a nice treat, or looking at the flash type we use on a camera trap. When an image is taken at night, you have the option of an infrared or a white flash, and, as anyone who has been to a photo shoot will know, a white flash can be very invasive. And we are also then looking at where to place those cameras, so do we need to be laying them out in a grid to cover a complete area, or could we be placing them more strategically on roads and trails? So that’s the broad overview, with the ultimate goal of having a final chapter that actually provides us with our first ever state-wide density estimate of feral cats in Tasmania. So, not just where are they in the state but in what numbers, and do they have preferred habitats and prey species? So, that’s all in the works at the moment.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: So these cameras can actually be there, when the creature turns up it triggers the flash and you’ve got a picture, and you turn up in the morning and you look at the camera, what it has taken and what’s there.

ALEXANDRA PATON: Yes, it’s not just every morning, it’s up to six months. So I tend to prefer white flash cameras. I can leave them in the environment for six months at a time, come back, take out the SD card, put in a fresh SD card, change the batteries and she’s good to go again. And if I’m in a really remote area, like Dr Jessie Buettel and Kenji and our research group, they are tracking out 20-odd kilometres into the south-west and deploying cameras, they leave those with the infrared flash and they can leave them for a year, so we’re getting a full year’s worth of data for regions that have never been monitored for wildlife in this way. So they are a really useful tool for ecologists.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: Obviously you don’t watch them for a year to see what has turned up. How do you monitor what you’ve got?

ALEXANDRA PATON: We take the SD card out of the camera after that time and we look at the images that are on them. That can be incredibly time-consuming when you are identifying to a species level, so Professor Barry Brook and his team have actually created a classifier, so it’s a kind of machine learning, not quite artificial intelligence but akin to it, where we’ve told a computer, okay, here’s 1,000 images of a wallaby, there you go, and then you show the computer another photo of a wallaby and it can tell you, oh yes, I recognise that. And it does the same thing with nearly all of our large mammals in Tasmania, so we go out, collect our SD cards, feed those images into the classifier, and that spits out all of our species.

The difficult part is then where I have to go in and pull out all the images of cats and analyse those by hand. So, not only do I go, okay, these are all cats, I also look at the coat colour of the cat, the behaviour of the cat on the camera, what is it doing, is it investigating the camera, is it just walking past? Does it have prey in its mouth, and, if so, what is it eating? I also then take a really close look at the cat and figure out who it is. So I assign an individual ID to all of our cats that display a coat pattern other than solid black, so I can actually keep track of where they are and what cameras they are moving to across the state. It’s very time-consuming.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: Is that the best way you get an idea of the population of cats around various parts of Tasmania?

ALEXANDRA PATON: Using camera traps, definitely you require that individual identification to the best of your ability. There have been some steps towards creating artificial intelligence or a classifier for individual ID, methods such as YOLO or ‘you only look once’, where you can feed in a very small collection of images and train a computer to identify the cat with about 60% to 70% accuracy. But that being said, that’s only really useful for a very long-term monitoring program, so if you’re expecting to monitor cats for tens of years, like they are doing on Kangaroo Island, then it’s great to use that kind of technology. But for me, my cameras are only going to be out for four years, so it’s less useful in that sense and it’s faster for me to do it by hand because I’d have to do it by hand anyway to give the computer something to be trained off.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: And what are you finding? Are you finding there are far more cats or fewer cats or what?

ALEXANDRA PATON: There’s definitely a lot of cats. I think what people don’t realise is you can say to people cats are everywhere and they will say, yes, of course they are, but then you show them an image of the mountains in the south-west or the coastline of the south-west to even, northwest, southeast, and there are just cats with these dramatic backdrops, truly living out in the wilderness where there are no people for hundreds and hundreds of kilometres, and it’s getting across the message that cats have been here since we colonised Tasmania and they have spread since that point. It’s not just people having cats outdoors now, they are truly multigenerational established species at this point. So I’m just now coming out with some of my estimates of density. So, occupancy, that is to say a cat resides in an area, we are looking at 89% for our 1,100 camera traps across the state.

When it comes to density, I’m starting to get some numbers for the west coast of Tasmania where we are looking at a home range of about 10 square kilometres for an individual cat. So, say, in 100 square kilometres you expect there to be about 10 cats as our density, but watch this space, more results are on the way and I’m hoping to have those kinds of numbers for every part of Tasmania.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: You hinted in the beginning that there’s got to be some way of treating the population, culling, who knows what. Once you’ve worked out sufficient numbers to get a proper clue as to how to approach this, what might you do?

ALEXANDRA PATON: Tasmania is a bit of a unique case compared to mainland Australia because we have these wonderful creatures living here called Tasmania Devils, which makes it very difficult to target cats without having some bycatch in some form. So, the traditional way of culling cats is through shooting. And, as anyone who has shot a gun will know, very difficult to do in a dense rainforest or wet eucalypt or even dry eucalypt forest. It can even take months to shoot a persistent tomcat in places like Macquarie Island where it is just scrub. It’s a very difficult endeavour and it’s near impossible in somewhere like Tasmania.

The other option traditionally used is baiting. This can be through aerial baits where you will drop little sausages with a poisoned pellet inside from the sky over the land and hope that a cat will come and eat it, or you might target those baits towards areas you expect cats to reside. The issue with using that method comes with the fact we know Devils and cats overlap significantly in the areas that they inhabit. So if you bait for cats, you are inevitably going to end up baiting for Devils, and they’ve already got enough on their plate with deadly facial tumour, we don’t need to poison them as well.

Our last option for control, traditionally speaking, is cage trapping, and cats are so trap shy. If you put out cages on your property, you might have noticed that you catch a lot of juvenile cats, but getting the established adults is incredibly difficult. So when I do find these density estimates across Tasmania, my hope is that we have the option to employ the new control methods that are coming out, things like the Felixer, a machine created by John Read that can recognise when a cat is walking past it, and it fires a paintball of poison at the animal. Cats being a grooming animal, they take a lot of care in looking after their coat, then lick off the poison and die. The benefit to such a machine is that you have a two-step targeting approach where it has to recognise the animal as a cat, and then even if it misfires, it has to be an animal that is going to lick that poison off its coat. So having an idea of how many cats are in Tasmania and where would be really beneficial so that if the Felixer becomes more widely available we can actually figure out, okay, where do we want to deploy these, where are there the highest densities of cats, where are we going to have the biggest impact? My hope is as well that other methods will arise similar to the Felixer, but I think they are still in the works at the moment.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: And to remind, I’m sure everyone really knows that the killing of native creatures is something like 3 billion…is it a year or more?

ALEXANDRA PATON: Yes, about that.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: 3 billion, it’s just incredible, the number of creatures that are knocked off by this invading, as you say, feral pet gone wild. But can you make much difference, even with the kind of advanced machinery that you describe?

ALEXANDRA PATON: At a large-scale at the moment, no. This might be controversial but cats have been here since we colonised and they spread rapidly across Tasmania. One could theorise that the damage they were likely to do initially has already been done for many of the rural parts of Tasmania, that is to say they’ve spread across the state and potentially had as much impact as they were going to have. What we need to think about now are how additional anthropogenic impacts are impacting our native wildlife in conjunction with feral cats. So, things like climate change, forestry, logging, development and other invasive species, making sure we don’t have another invasion. We know that on the mainland cats are bad on their own, foxes are bad on their own, but together they are greater than the sum of their parts and we don’t want to see something like that in Tasmania.

So, while there is not a lot we can do on mainland Tasmania or even mainland Australia at this point, what we can do is focus on island eradication. So, my hope is that these technologies can be deployed on the islands surrounding Australia and Tasmania to actually create some safe havens so that those species that are at threat, not just from cats but from other human impacts, have somewhere where we can keep them safe while we develop new technologies to hopefully eradicate cats.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: And meanwhile keep your cats and your pets in the house.

ALEXANDRA PATON: Yes, absolutely. It’s a little-known fact that domestic cats per square kilometre are actually having about 35 times the impact as feral cats for the same amount of area and a wilderness area. So the idea is that if you think about a feral cat, this is an animal that is living tooth and nail, it is going out and hunting, defending its territory, and they are territorial, if a tomcat enters another tomcat’s realm, there’s going to be a showdown. But they are only territorial because resources are limited. So you jump over to an urban environment where we have houses upon houses upon houses, and every third or fourth or fifth house has a cat, depending on where you are, well, those cats don’t have a resource shortage, they have food and water and a warm bed night. Heck, some of these cats might have multiple households feeding them. So there is no fight for territory. So then we can end up with a much greater density of cats living in that urban area, so of course their impact on wildlife is going to be far, far greater.

The issue comes in again when people think that, oh, I only ever see blackbirds around my house, or I only ever see brown rats, so there is no harm in my cat going outside and killing them. Well, of course you’re only seeing those animals because the native animals have no chance to establish because they are competing with those invasive species, and now your cat that’s eating them. And we know that Australian animals are naïve to predators that are invasive, and this is a big problem with cats again. So yes, please keep your cats indoors, you can have movie nights with them and show them YouTube videos of birds, you can train your cat to walk on a leash, I have done it, it’s possible. There are so many alternatives. You really should treat your cat like a dog. And, as an added bonus, outdoor cats’ life expectancy is about seven to eight years, indoor cats, 21. So if you love your pet, you will keep it inside.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: Do you have a cat?

ALEXANDRA PATON: I do have a cat, yes, she’s a rescue cat, a ginger female, which is very rare. Yes, she was in her former life an outdoor roaming cat, and we have tenderly and lovingly trained her to be an indoor cat. And while it is a bit of a journey, I think it was really important for me to undertake so I could empathise with cat owners and give that advice of how do you rehabilitate your pet cat to be indoors only, and it is possible and they still have an amazing quality of life, if not better because when a cat gets hit by a car and limps for the rest of its days, or worse, it’s not really a great quality of life.

ROBYN WILLIAMS: No, it’s not. Instead, picture Alexa with her ginger cat strolling safely through the groves of Hobart. She’s doing her PhD at the University of Tasmania.</text>
        <interlocutors>Robyn Williams, Alexandra Paton</interlocutors>
        <source>https://www.abc.net.au/radionational/programs/scienceshow/getting-the-cameras-right-to-count-feral-cats/13924350</source>
    </conversation>
    <conversation>
        <text>NORMAN SWAN: Hello, and welcome to the Health Report with me, Norman Swan. Today, the genetic mutations that see cancer risks cascade through generations of families.

MICHELLE BRADY: I was, like, how does a 14-year-old child get a second primary cancer? You know, this is not a spread. That doesn’t happen, there is obviously something more going on.

ANNA MURPHY: I think it’s there every day, it’s like you look in the mirror and you see scars from surgeries you’ve had. I don’t think I don’t go a day without thinking of it.

NORMAN SWAN: More than two decades ago, a major milestone in cancer was reached with the discovery of the BRCA1 and BRCA2 genes. Inherited mutations to these genes can dramatically increase the risk of developing breast and ovarian cancers. This knowledge opened up new ways of knowing who is at risk of cancer, how to treat it and even how to prevent the cancer ever happening in the first place. Since then, many more inherited gene mutations have been found, linked to other types of cancer. What does this mean for the families that have seen generations of loved ones endure sometimes multiple cancers? And the emerging frontier in medicine trying to change that. This feature has been made by Sarah Sedghi.

MICHELLE BRADY: Addie was…wow, she was an incredible young child, very, very bright, very, very beautiful. I know a lot of parents say that about their children but she truly was. She had a zest for life and that all came crumbling down when she was just nine years old.

SARAH SEDGHI: Michelle Brady remembers how brave and selfless her daughter was as she went through treatment for a rare form of bone cancer. Her tibia had to be removed and was replaced by a prosthetic bone in her leg, and there were months in hospital having chemotherapy. Michelle says her daughter adapted, recovered and continued to live her life fully and joyfully.

MICHELLE BRADY: I call it like a blip in her life and life would carry on, and it did. And then when she was 14 she got up one morning and just out of the blue, there were no signs of any of this, this is five years on from her first cancer, she was unable to speak and she had a seizure and she was rushed to hospital by an ambulance. And in a couple of days after that, we were advised that she had an inoperable brain tumour. Treatment was only available to extend life rather than save life, which was incredibly hard for us as parents to hear.

SARAH SEDGHI: Michelle Brady knew something more was going on. It didn’t make sense that her young daughter could have two different cancers in such a short time.

MICHELLE BRADY: And deep down I know, even at 14, Addie knew the seriousness of cancer because at nine years old she had experienced it, she had seen children that she had been on the ward with lose their lives to cancer, so she knew, and she knew that a brain tumour was really, really bad. And during the time before we did lose her, she asked me probably twice, ‘Am I going to die, Mum?’ And it was probably the toughest questions I’ve ever had to answer, but I think deep down Addie knew where it was going.

And especially the last few months of Addie’s life, the cancer really became quite brutal. It moved to her spine, so it ended up taking her mobility. It then started impacting her sight. Trying to get on top of the pain for Addie was very, very hard, and it was brutal. I saw a change in her…I wouldn’t say personality, her personality was always there and it was always trying to break through and shine through, but it became a tough fight for her because trying to deal with living with pain constantly was a struggle, and you saw it started to have an impact on her, and the bright beautiful Addie that we knew started to change, and that was heartbreaking, to watch her experience that and for us watching her go through it and not being able to do anything about it.

SARAH SEDGHI: Addie died in February 2018. She was only 16 years old. When Michelle tells me about her daughter’s warmth and radiance, she says her daughter wouldn’t want her to be sad, she’d want her family to continue to love life as much as she did. Michelle’s instincts about the cause of Addie’s cancer had been right. After Addie had been diagnosed with cancer a second time, genetic testing revealed she had Li-Fraumeni Syndrome or LFS. It’s an inherited mutation to the TP53 gene. The gene is known as the guardian of the genome because it stops cancers from forming, but for people with LFS, this process goes awry and the gene can’t always stop cancer from forming. It leaves people at risk of multiple cancers. Discovering this mutation can have generational consequences as it can be inherited, but in Addie’s case she had what’s known as a de novo mutation, meaning the first person in the family to have the mutation.

In a Sydney lab, researchers are using tumour cells from children with cancer to see what drugs they respond well to. It’s just one part of the emerging field of precision medicine, a growing frontier in cancer treatment.

MARK PINESE: Really our vision is that one day there will be a time when children do not have to be treated for their cancer, and that’s what my team is really working towards.

SARAH SEDGHI: Dr Mark Pinese is the team leader of Personalised Medicine at the Children’s Cancer Institute. His team is looking at inherited and de novo gene variants some children are born with that put them at risk of cancer.

MARK PINESE: If we can identify those kids who are at risk of cancer, then in the future we might be able to have drugs at hand that we can give these children, relatively minor drugs that they can take that will take away their risk, that they just don’t develop cancer at all, and that for us is the ultimate goal and so much better than a cure.

SARAH SEDGHI: For all cancers, whether beginning in childhood or adulthood, there are genetic changes that occur, and usually factors like lifestyle and the environment are involved too, but here we are talking about cancer-causing gene changes that are inherited, not acquired. Having an inherited gene mutation is not a guarantee that cancer will develop, but it does put people at much higher risk, often at a younger age. The type of mutation determines how high that risk is. Inherited genes are behind 5% to 10% of all cancers.

MARK PINESE: Precision medicine is maturing, so the idea was in the start we look at a tumour, we find out what makes that tumour tick and then we find the drug for it. I think now we are starting to look even broader and we are starting to understand, well, the tumour is only part of the story. What genes was that child born with? That’s also important. Can we bring information from that in to better treat the cancer as well, and I think more and more we are seeing that that’s the case, that looking together in a holistic way at what a child is born with, what is going on in their tumour and how we can target both aspects of that is the way to the best outcomes.

SARAH SEDGHI: Researchers like Dr Mark Pinese have high hopes of what precision medicine can do for those born with cancer risks. For some people it might mean knowing what drug to give them that will respond well to the mutation they have, to either treat a cancer or stop it forming in the first place. For others it could mean that preventative surgery, like some women with BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutations, for whom a preventative mastectomy and removal of their ovaries can reduce the chances of breast and ovarian cancer developing by up to 95%. Whatever the age of the patient or the cancer type, treatment would be targeted and personalised. For children with cancer, it would be an enormous leap in how things are done. Currently treatment for childhood cancer is often harsh and unspecific because much of the research on treatments to date has been done on adults.

MARK PINESE: Very sadly, many children who survive cancer do so with long-term side-effects. These can be lifelong effects on their fertility, on their growth and development, on their learning. And we are as much as possible trying to minimise that and we honestly are finding that if we can find targeted treatments, we believe that that will minimise side-effects as well.

SARAH SEDGHI: Another tool being used for people at high risk of cancer from inherited mutations is surveillance, that’s following up people to see if there has been a re-occurrence or a new cancer that has developed that could be treated early. But it’s a double-edged sword.

MARK PINESE: We started that program a number of years ago, and at this stage it’s proven to be a very successful program in which we have been able to pick up a number of diagnoses at a very early stage, and I think we are very confident that that has made a big difference.

ANNA MURPHY: In cancer land we tend to call it scanxiety, but we have to think of it as a blessing that we know about it.

SARAH SEDGHI: Across multiple states in Australia right now, a clinical trial known as SMOC is being run. It’s using MRIs and other surveillance for people at high risk of developing cancer, particularly multiple types of cancer like those with Li-Fraumeni Syndrome. Professor Paul James is a clinical geneticist and the director of the Familial Cancer Centre at the Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre and Royal Melbourne Hospital.

PAUL JAMES: In the past, people have always looked at Li-Fraumeni Syndrome as a situation where the risk was very high but there wasn’t an awful lot that we could do about it because it was a complex risk that involved lots of different types of cancer. But this trial has really showed that actually there is a lot more that we could do and if we take a very active approach we can actually make a difference, even in a condition that has such a high risk as Li-Fraumeni Syndrome.

SARAH SEDGHI: There used to be view in medicine that knowing these genetic risks was often futile because not enough was known about how to prevent or treat associated cancers. But Professor James says that’s shifting, and he is optimistic about where precision medicine is heading.

PAUL JAMES: In the past we just didn’t have enough information or awareness of the people who were at risk in the population, and so there wasn’t much we could do because it was really beyond us to identify that risk. Now we have the tools to identify it, I think that fatalistic view has really been replaced by a view that if we know who is at risk then there is much more that we can do and there’s opportunities in every situation.

Sometimes the implications are quite confronting, but in comparison to simply saying, 'oh well, there’s nothing we can do about it, some people will develop that cancer in childhood and that’s just the way it goes’, I think we have definitely moved on beyond that point and there’s really no type of cancer where we would say we can’t really tackle that, they are all situations now where if we have the right information and we understand the genetics, then there is definitely more we can do.

Anna Murphy: When I first found out, it was pretty hard to take, I was absolutely devastated when I found out that I actually had it because it’s quite a rare mutation, and because I’ve already had cancer three times already, it was sort of like a real kick in the guts to me, like, wow, now I’ve got to worry about so many more cancers.

SARAH SEDGHI: Anna Murphy lives with a mutation to the BAP1 gene. It’s rare and puts her at risk of multiple cancers. Anna has already had cancer three times but none were related to her inherited BAP1 gene mutation.

ANNA MURPHY: I have got a son, he was only six years old when I was first diagnosed with cancer, and he’s sort of lived through all three cancers with me, saw his mother sick and all the rest of it. And when I was diagnosed with this mutation I said my biggest fear was that my son was going to have it, and unfortunately he does have it. But like I said to him, we have to think of it as a blessing that we know about it and that we are both being tested for everything. I’ve got to be thankful that we know about it so that we are constantly being screened, so if something does turn up or reappears somewhere, it will be caught early.

SARAH SEDGHI: Anna is part of the SMOC trial and has yearly full-body MRIs. If a cancer is there, the hope is it will be picked up and treated straight away. While she is grateful to be part of the trial, the constant threat of cancer weighs heavily on her.

ANNA MURPHY: Every time I have a scan, in cancer land we tend to call it scan anxiety. You know you’ve got a test coming up and you don’t get results obviously straight away, so it’s always there, it’s always going to be there, that anxiety or just in the back of your head, like what if it has come back. I don’t think it just ever goes away, just the constant fear of recurrence and that. It gets probably a little bit easier, but it just finds a way to still stay in there, don’t worry.

SARAH SEDGHI: How often do you think about cancer?

ANNA MURPHY: Oh wow, well, it sort of…I think it’s there every day, it’s like you look in the mirror and you see scars and you see scars from surgeries you’ve had or…I think it’s something…I don’t think I don’t go a day without thinking of it, I think, to be honest. I think it’s just part of me, as much as I don’t want it to be part of me, it has just been such a big part of my life that it’s not something I can just switch off. I can control it, it doesn’t overwhelm me and things like that, but it’s just something that you are reminded of every day when you look in the mirror.

SARAH SEDGHI: You’re listening to the Health Report on Radio National. This is a special feature on the genetics of cancer. I’m Sarah Sedghi.

Most cancers are acquired, brought about through damage to a person’s cells, say from smoking, other toxins, or lifestyle issues. But these inherited mutations, while less common, can have devastating effects on generations of families. So how would you know if you’re at risk?

PAUL JAMES: The standard way of thinking about identifying people who might have an increased risk based on a genetic cause is to think about family history, and that’s still a very good guide.

SARAH SEDGHI: As useful as knowing your family history is, Professor Paul James says it’s only part of the picture.

PAUL JAMES: It only picks up about half of the people who carry an underlying gene mutation and that’s just because some people don’t know their family history, some people’s families aren’t that large, and so there’s really not been much of a chance for a family history to occur, and in some cases these are cancers which, for instance the case of ovarian cancer and breast cancer, they are male or female specific, and so if it has come down from the other side of the family, so if you have a breast cancer gene coming down from the male side of the family, the family history may not be there.

SARAH SEDGHI: The type of cancer and age of onset can also offer insight as to whether an inherited gene is behind it.

PAUL JAMES: And so these days we are also focusing a lot more on particular types of cancers, things like people who have a diagnosis at a young age, and those can also be really good clues about who we should be offering genetic testing to. And even there’s a lot more interest now in offering this type of testing quite widely, maybe even as a screening test in the population, and there has been some good studies that have looked at how this would work if we were to offer the testing to everybody as part of a plan to work out the right recommendations for people in terms of screening and follow-up into the future. And so it maybe that as the genetic testing becomes more available, we can start to think beyond those standard risk factors like family history and age and start to think about using it for nearly everybody to work out your underlying cancer risk.

SARAH SEDGHI: Learning you have an inherited mutation can be confronting. While some mutations may only raise your risk slightly, others mean the likelihood of cancer is very high. One of the essential sources of information, advice and support for those affected, is a genetic counsellor.

LAURA FORREST: We talk about how they can manage those cancer risks, so for some people that might mean thinking about having risk reducing surgery. For other people it might mean attending regular cancer screening.

SARAH SEDGHI: Dr Laura Forrest is a senior research fellow and genetic counsellor at the Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre. She has done extensive studies into people’s experiences living with hereditary cancer risk.

LAURA FORREST: Young people who have hereditary cancer syndromes will engage in cancer screening because it offers them a sense of control and it can offer them a sense of hope as well, some peace of mind over this threat that they may develop cancer. And we heard from our research that a lot of young people thought this is really their best shot at controlling their health with regard to this hereditary cancer syndrome. But some people also commented that on the flipside there is this real tension, they engage in this screening, but for some cancer syndromes, like Li-Fraumeni, they actually have no other options, it’s screening or nothing. For some of them they actually felt that they had lost control because that was their only option and they couldn’t choose anything else.

SARAH SEDGHI: She also knows through her work as a genetic counsellor and through her research how difficult some decisions around cancer prevention can be, like for those women for whom a mastectomy will give them their best hope of stopping breast cancer.

LAURA FORREST: They are huge surgeries and they really can’t be underestimated. Young women who choose to have a bilateral prophylactic mastectomy tend to have very little tolerance for their cancer risk. So a lot of young women will choose to have this surgery because they just want to rule out breast cancer completely and they are willing to engage in this big surgery because they want to be there for their children, they talk about wanting to be alive for their children. Many of these young women, because their family histories are riddled with their previous female relatives who have gone on to develop breast cancer and often had really bad outcomes, they want to do everything within their power to not develop breast cancer because they want to be there for their children, they want to be there for their children growing up.

SARAH SEDGHI: CDH1 is another hereditary mutation that puts people at risk of diffuse stomach cancer. It’s not an easy cancer to pick up early, so those with the mutation may choose to have their stomach removed to prevent cancer. It’s a life altering surgery.

Laura Forrest: Clinical guidelines recommend that young people have that surgery if they have a CDH1 gene change. They are recommended to have gastrectomy between the ages of 20 and 30 years of age. The consequences of the surgery can include things like it can really impact your body image, it impacts the way you eat, and of course food is so involved in how we socialise. It can have really far-reaching impacts, and yet people with the CDH1 gene change will still choose to have this surgery where they have their entire stomach removed, again, to make sure that they are there for their children, that they are alive for their children.

SARAH SEDGHI: I mentioned earlier in this program that one of the goals of precision medicine for those who have inherited risk and go on to develop cancer is to find a drug or drug combination that their particular cancer will respond to. Professor Paul James says a phase 3 clinical trial known as OlympiA has had some of the most promising results for women with breast cancer.

PAUL JAMES: OlympiA was a very exciting result, it was looking at individuals with this type of breast cancer, triple negative breast cancer, and it was looking at the idea that an underlying gene mutation in BRCA1 or BRCA2 could help guide the treatment for those types of cancer, and the outcome was very successful. They were trialling a drug called Olaparib which is a targeted therapy which is designed to expose a vulnerability in the cancer which occurs because it has an underlying gene mutation in BRCA1 or BRCA2, and what they showed is if that genetic fault was there in the gene in either an inherited form or if it even had just occurred in the cancer itself, then Olaparib was a very successful treatment and was amongst the most successful trials that there has been in the last few years for breast cancer, so a very exciting result and one which is likely to have a big impact on the way that breast cancer management is done in the future. And that’s a good example of how important this genetic information is becoming, not just for the traditional reason of trying to identify individuals at high risk but also even once diagnosis occurs, increasingly the genetic information plays a big role in working out what is the best treatment for that person and targeting specific aspects of their cancer. That’s an area that is advancing very quickly and is likely to apply to more and more genes into the future.

SARAH SEDGHI: The discovery of the BRCA1 and BRCA2 gene mutations more than two decades ago was just the start, Professor James says. As more genes have been discovered, more possibilities for treatment and prevention have followed. But precision medicine is really still only in its infancy. There’s still much to learn.

PAUL JAMES: There’s nothing more personal to you than your own genetic make-up, and everybody’s genetic make-up is unique, and using that information to work out in what way your own requirements in terms of both preventative measures, things to reduce your risk of cancer, and then if you have a diagnosis, in what way your genetics informs the best treatment for you, that’s really a key part of the idea of targeted therapies or targeted screening programs that are actually designed or tailored towards exactly what you need based on your underlying genetics.

And so you’d hear a lot about personalised programs that include a number of different elements, but genetics or genomics which is looking more broadly at every variation right across your genome, those are things which are really core to the idea of personalisation and precision medicine.

SARAH SEDGHI: Right now much of what is known about hereditary risk focuses on single gene mutations. Professor Paul James says researchers are also turning their attention to how multiple genes interact with each other.

PAUL JAMES: Just at the moment we are at the point where we are starting to really think about even more complex genetic risks, so instead of the risk being due to one large genetic fault that occurs in a single gene, we are starting to think about the way that genetic variations across the genome start to interact with each other and can cause their risk by being added up together, so a compound effect where all the different genetic variants actually come together to produce the risk, so it’s not any one variant that’s important now, it’s the burden of different variants that come together to cause the risk. And that’s a type of testing that would allow us to really offer genetic testing to anybody and provide an assessment of their risk, and that’s known as polygenic risk, and that’s just starting to come through now as something that we are beginning to be able to look at, at least in the research setting. And so we’ve got a number of trials looking at both risk prevention for high risk genes but also now whether or not polygenic risk can also contribute to those types of risk assessment processes and improve our ability to identify the people that we want to offer more targeted screening or targeted risk prevention to.

MICHELLE BRADY: People living under the cloud of Li-Fraumeni, it’s a tough life I would say. It’s hard for me to say what their lives are like, but I can imagine that living in…and I know many of the families don’t live in fear but it’s an umbrella that they live under, you know, the constant worry if a little lump comes up on their hand or they start feeling a pain in a certain part of their body. It’s a constant worry in the back of their heads, it’s a constant life of being tested, MRIs, dealing with treatments, dealing with the next cancer coming along. And to live with that constantly, I can imagine, it can be quite dark at times and challenging.

SARAH SEDGHI: Michelle Brady continues her daughter Addie’s legacy by supporting families and research into hereditary cancer syndromes like LFS.

MICHELLE BRADY: If I can help families going through it, then that’s only something positive that can come from losing someone like Addie because she had, like I said, such zest for life, and I know for me going forward…a lot of people say to me how do you cope, you know, how do you do this, why do you do this? And I do it because of Addie, simply because of that, because I know that she wouldn’t want me to carry on through life just mourning her death, she’d want me to do something because of what happened to her. So if that’s helping us supporting other families, then that’s surely only a good thing.

SARAH SEDGHI: This has been the Health Report, I’m Sarah Sedghi. Norman Swan and Tegan Taylor will be back with you at the same time next week.</text>
        <interlocutors>Sarah Sedghi, Michelle Brady, Paul James, Laura Forrest, Anna Murphy, Norman Swan, Mark Pinese</interlocutors>
        <source>https://www.abc.net.au/radionational/programs/healthreport/the-cancer-risks-that-run-through-generations/13924132</source>
    </conversation>
    <conversation>
        <text>TEGAN TAYLOR: When my babies were a couple of days old, they were taken to a special room, fitted with cool-looking headphones and sensors and then they proceeded to sleep as a series of soft noises were played to them. It was part of my state’s newborn hearing program, it’s an initiative that helps with very early detection of hearing problems, but these problems only pick up on some of the hearing loss that can lead to issues with speech, language and learning down the track. In fact, more than one in ten kids from disadvantaged backgrounds have hearing loss by the time they’re in school, and that can potentially compound their disadvantage. So, how can we improve?

Cath McMahon from Macquarie University is an author on some recent papers looking into this, and she joins us now. Hi Cath.

CATH MCMAHON: Hi Tegan, how are you?

TEGAN TAYLOR: Good. What happens when hearing loss isn’t detected in young kids?

CATH MCMAHON: It’s difficult to detect hearing loss in some cases in young kids, but the challenges are that they don’t develop good listening skills, they don’t develop their ability to learn how to attend to things. And of course that has a knock-on effect of them developing good social skills but also, as you mentioned, the speech and language delays, which can really affect their readiness to start school.

TEGAN TAYLOR: So who is most at risk?

CATH MCMAHON: Well, the kids that are most at risk are those from lower socio-economic environments, and it really does come down to the social determinants of health, good hygiene, good nutrition, overcrowding in houses. And in many cases it’s not just an issue of hearing loss, it’s middle ear disease which then will cause hearing loss that’s a problem.

TEGAN TAYLOR: Right, so it’s a complex thing, it’s not just hearing, there’s other health factors that are going into it. But your research is focusing mostly on the hearing side because of those knock-on effects that it has. If you’re talking about kids who are at high risk of disadvantage, they are probably less likely to have good access to medical services anyway, so how do you then go about adding in another intervention which is a screening program when they are already less likely to perhaps have access to good medical interventions?

CATH MCMAHON: Yes, I think we need to first be really aware that hearing loss is a major public health problem and the implication that it does have on kids particularly around school time when you really do see that exponential trajectory of learning that occurs, there are multiple ways that we could do it. A simple, simple way is that when a child has a health check, that you could integrate an ear and hearing check. And if you did recognise hearing loss as being a major public health problem that it would just be a no-brainer to have these ear and hearing checks within these complex health checks. You know, I look at vision and we have really good programs for vision checks before kids start school, but we just don’t have the same things for hearing.

TEGAN TAYLOR: Yes, it’s interesting, isn’t it, either someone is perhaps profoundly deaf but then that spectrum of hearing loss isn’t really considered as much in the realm of physical health as so many other things are.

CATH MCMAHON: Absolutely, and it’s definitely not binary, it’s not you either have a hearing loss or you don’t, it’s the grades of hearing loss that become important. And the reason I spoke about middle ear disease is because often the hearing loss is fluctuating in nature, and so it’s complicated to detect a problem until often the implications of the hearing loss become quite profound. So the speech and language is delayed, and then there really does need to be attention focused to address that.

But one of the things that we can do better which I think is really important as well is to have greater partnerships across education and health. You know, teachers are ideally positioned in schools to be able to identify challenges that kids might have, to identify some of these speech and language delays or even to identify those kids who are acting up in class because sometimes it’s simply that they can’t hear, it’s not necessarily that they are naughty kids.

TEGAN TAYLOR: Right. So in addition to…if it was part of that child health screening that you mentioned before, what other aspects would you like to see included in a national program for kids and hearing loss?

CATH MCMAHON: It’s not just the hearing loss that we need to check, it really is the middle ears as well. But when you introduced the piece you are talking about your own kids having gone through newborn hearing screening, but we know that about 50% of hearing loss in school-age kids is not detected by that, and so we really need better ways to be able to check them along that path from when they are very young all the way through to school because it is quite a quantum leap to only have checks from the time they’re born to checks at school, so there are multiple ways you can embed ear and hearing checks into regular health checks. But really if we can also identify those kids who are most at risk and then there are some really interesting programs where they have combined ear and hearing checks with vaccination programs, which is a fantastic opportunity to be able to detect a problem at a regular health check or a regular time at which the child is coming into a health clinic.

TEGAN TAYLOR: That’s fantastic. Really briefly, are there any places that are doing this very well?

CATH MCMAHON: Globally? Not really.

TEGAN TAYLOR: No, in Australia.

CATH MCMAHON: So what I wanted to mention is that there is a game based app which has been beautifully designed, it’s called Sound Scouts, and in fact the federal government put money into this program, and it’s available to schoolkids. But the rollout of the program hasn’t been particularly good, and I think we really need to raise awareness about what the challenge is…

TEGAN TAYLOR: We do have to leave it there, Cath, but Sound Scouts is the one that you are mentioning, and I’ll get people to maybe look it up on their phones or on their search engines if they can. Cath, thanks for joining us.

CATH MCMAHON: Thanks Tegan, bye-bye.

TEGAN TAYLOR: Professor Cath McMahon is the head of the Department of Linguistics at Macquarie University.</text>
        <interlocutors>Tegan Taylor, Cath Mcmahon</interlocutors>
        <source>https://www.abc.net.au/radionational/programs/healthreport/screening-kids-for-hearing-loss/13704428</source>
    </conversation>
    <conversation>
        <text>DAN ROAN: Is it sad for you to see Manchester United not quite at the level they were before?

CRISTIANO RONALDO: For me it’s hard to see that because it’s a club that I love. Of course I want to see Manchester United at the level that it was in the past. Like, for example, Sporting Lisbon was my first professional club. I like to see the clubs that I like at the top and I think Manchester this season is better, but I think they still have work to do to be at the level of six, seven years ago.

DAN ROAN: What possibility is there of you going back to Manchester United one day?

CRISTIANO RONALDO: As I say many, many times, the future nobody knows. At this moment I’m so glad and happy here in Real Madrid but the future nobody knows. I will say this answer all the time because the future nobody knows, but I’m good here. I still have a contract with Real Madrid and I’m happy here.

DAN ROAN: You’ve made a film [Ronaldo, released on Monday] telling your life story. What’s it like being a footballing superstar?

CRISTIANO RONALDO: It’s great. This has given me motivation to still work hard and better in my job but I have to say to be in my shoes is not easy. But I’m not complaining. I just want to say that. I feel happy. All this happens because of a reason. The reason is I’m unbelievable inside the pitch. This is why the people have so much interest on me. So it’s as simple as that. I’m good, I’m happy, I’m motivated all the time. I’m very professional and I want to carry on like that.

DAN ROAN: You played under Jose Mourinho for three seasons here at Real Madrid. He’s going through a tough spell now. Are you surprised by that?

CRISTIANO RONALDO: I’m not surprised because in football anything can happen. Of course, he’s a manager that I was working with for two years and I know his potential. I know that not just him but Chelsea are in this tough situation. As a Portuguese man, I want to see the Portuguese at the top level all the time. So this is what I wish for him that he can go through this bad situation and make Chelsea fans happy because they deserve it.</text>
        <interlocutors>Dan Roan, Cristiano Ronaldo</interlocutors>
        <source>https://www.bbc.com/sport/football/34737914</source>
    </conversation>
    <conversation>
        <text>CRISTIANO RONALDO: “I never saw the video. (Crying). I never saw that video. Unbelievable.”

PIERS MORGAN: “To hear your father speak about how proud he was of you must mean a lot to you.“

CRISTIANO RONALDO: “Yes, a lot. I think the interview would be funny, but I didn’t expect to cry. But I never saw these images. I don’t know where you … I have to have these images to show my family. But I really don’t know my father 100%. He was a drunk person. I never spoke with him, like a normal conversation. It was hard.”

PIERS MORGAN: “What’s the sadness for you?”

CRISTIANO RONALDO: “To be the number one, and he don’t see nothing, and he don’t see to receive awards, to see what I …”

PIERS MORGAN: “He never saw how great you became.”

CRISTIANO RONALDO: “Never. Never.“

PIERS MORGAN: “What you could see from that interview was how much it would have meant to him, I think, was very clear.”

CRISTIANO RONALDO: “Yes.”

PIERS MORGAN: “He clearly had a huge pride.“

CRISTIANO RONALDO: “My family see, my mum, my brothers, even my old son, but my father, he didn’t see nothing, and it was – he died young.”</text>
        <interlocutors>Cristiano Ronaldo, Piers Morgan</interlocutors>
        <source>https://www.mirror.co.uk/sport/football/news/cristiano-ronaldo-interview-live-piers-20083451</source>
    </conversation>
</game>
